Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communications Workers of America PE.023
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communications Workers of America
1941-2008
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.023
12 Linear Feet in 11 record cartons and 3 shared boxes
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communications Workers of America (1941-2008) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The collection consists of contracts, agreements, constitutions, convention proceedings, and reports, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, circular letters, newspapers clippings, pamphlets, and publications. A substantial portion of the material comes from the national body of the CWA and its various departments, however there is also material in the collection from districts and locals from around the country, but largely from locals in and around the New York area.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within Series I and II. Series III is described at the box level. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: General Files, 1946-2008
Series II: Districtd and Locals, 1941-2006
Series III: Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008
Historical Note
The Communications Workers of America was founded in 1947, the culmination of over fifty years of organizing efforts in the telephone industry. During the next twenty-five years and under the leadership of Joseph A. Beirne the CWA moved aggressively to organize all the telephone workers in the United States. AT&T with its monopolistic control resisted. It was, however, not until 1974 after years of labor-management unrest and a series of strikes that AT&T agreed to system wide collective bargaining. Shortly after the national contract was signed Beirne died and was replaced as President by Secretary-Treasurer Glenn E. Watts.
In the 1980s the CWA began to expand beyond telecommunications creating a Public Employees Department that successfully organized 34,000 New Jersey state workers in 1981. In 1985 Morton Bahr became the CWA President. The CWA continued to grow due to a series of mergers. In 1987 the it merged with the International Typographical Workers Union, in 1992 it absorbed the National Association of Broadcast Employees, and in 1995 the Newspaper Guild merged with the CWA as well.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America (WAG 124)
Communications Workers of America, Addendum (WAG 124.1)
Communications Workers of America, District 1 Records (WAG 117)
Communications Workers of America, District 2 Records (WAG 218)
Communications Workers of America, Local 1150 Records (WAG 59)
Communications Workers of America, Local 1151 Records (WAG 244)
Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 Records (WAG 132)
Communications Workers of America, Local 1172 Records (WAG 93)
Communications Workers of America, Local 1180 Records (WAG 63)
Communications Workers of America, Local 1250 Records (WAG 258)
Communications Workers of America, Local 2150 Records (WAG 229)
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communications Workers of America (1941-2008) consists of contracts, agreements, constitutions, convention proceedings, and reports, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, circular letters, newspapers clippings, pamphlets and publications.
Series I: General Files (1946-2008) consists of a broad range of printed material published by and collected about the Communications Workers of America. There are constitutions and convention proceedings as well as reports from executive board members. In this series there are also a number of files on prominent leaders and staff members of the Communications Workers of America. These files include material on CWA Presidents and national officers, Joseph Beirne, Glenn Watts, Morton Bahr and Barbara Easterling as well as leaders in various locals and districts. There are pamphlets and publications put out by the Education and Training Departments, including songbooks and manuals, as well as numerous brochures outlining membership in the CWA, benefits, union democracy, and collective bargaining among other basic facts about unions. This series contains several works outlining the history of telephone workers and organizing in the telephone industry, as well as numerous clippings documenting a broad range of events in CWA history. Information about important strikes from 1947-2000, including the 1989 strike with NYNEX, can also be found in this series.
Series II: Districts and Locals (1941-2006) contains material generated by the locals and districts of the Communications Workers of America all across the United States. However, the activities of locals from the New York and New Jersey area are better represented. Included in this series, is material on various rank and file committees of Local 1101 of New York City, including the publication The Bell Wringer, as well as the United Action Caucus and the Telephone Workers Legal Defense Committee. The Workers Education Local 189, once a part of the American Federation of Labor and now known as the United Association for Labor Education, sent out informative mailings and newsletters, the collection contains a sampling of these mailings from 1994-2000, as well as directories to labor education.
Series III: Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008, consists of five boxes of agreements and contracts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. The accession number associated with this collection is 2014.020.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- United States.; Labor unions; Labor unions -- New York (State); Fliers (printed matter); Labor unions -- Organizing -- New York (N.Y.); Labor unions -- New York (N.Y.); Contracts; Constitutions.; Printed ephemera.; Clippings (information artifacts); Circular letters.; Pamphlets.; Publications (documents); Agreements.; Telephone companies -- Employees -- Labor unions.; Strikes and lockouts -- Telephone companies -- New York (State); Telephone companies -- Employees -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Workers Education Local 189 (U.S.); Communications Workers of America. Local 1180 (New York, N.Y.); Communications Workers of America. District 1; Communications Workers of America
- Series I: General Files, 1946-2008; 5.5 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons and 2 oversize shared boxes
  - Allen, Clara, 1966-2007 (Box 1)
  - AT&T: Employee Assistance Program, 1981, undated (Box 1)
  - AT&T: Long Lines Department, 1962-1980, undated (Box 1)
  - AT&T: Political Action Committee (PAC), 1984 (Box 1)
  - Bahr, Morton (National President), 1955-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - Bahr, Morton (National President), 2000-2007 (Box 1)
  - Ballots (oversize), 1946 (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS004, Folder 3)
  - Beaumont, Dina George (Executive Assistant to National President), 1983-2005 (Box 1)
  - Beirne, Joseph (National President), 1964-2004, undated (Box 1)
  - Beirne, Joseph (National President): The Reminiscences of Joseph Beirne, Oral History Transcript, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Beirne, Joseph (National President): Publications by, 1962-1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Bell System, 1949-1977, undated (Box 1)
  - Bell System: Collective Bargaining and Settlements, 1965, 1971-1983 (Box 1)
  - Between the Lines (New York, NY), 1973 (Box 1)
  - Brochures (I), circa 1960-1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures (II), circa 1960-1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures (III), circa 1960-1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures (IV), circa 1960-1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Bryant, Connie (Locals 1181 and 1182), undated (Box 1)
  - Calendars and Date Books, 1972, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Oversize), 1946-1972 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001, Folder 1)
  - Cohen, Larry (National Vice-President), 2003-2004 (Box 1)
  - Collins, Eleanore (Local 1153), 1960-1989 (Box 1)
  - Committee of the Future, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Equity, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee on Political Education, 1978-1984, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1949, 1951, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1952-1959 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1960-1969 (Box 2)
  - Constitutions, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - Constitutions, 1976-1979 (Box 2)
  - Constitutions, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
  - Constitutions, 1984-1992 (Box 2)
  - Constitutions (Oversize), 1946, 1951 (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS004, Folder 2)
  - Conventions, 1947-1952 (Box 2)
  - Conventions, 1953-1959 (Box 2)
  - Conventions, 1961-1968 (Box 2)
  - Conventions, 1970-1974 (Box 2)
  - Conventions, 1975-1981 (Box 2)
  - Conventions, 1983-2008 (Box 2)
  - Conventions: Report of the Executive Board, 1951-1959 (Box 2)
  - Conventions: Report of the Executive Board, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Conventions: Report of the Executive Board, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Conventions: Report of the Executive Board, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Conventions: Report of the Executive Board, 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Cramer, Gus and June (National Vice-President), 1981 (Box 2)
  - Defense Fund, 1957, 1970, undated (Box 2)
  - Demsey, Edward (Local 1101), 1976 (Box 2)
  - Easterling, Barbara (Local 4302, Akron, OH and National Secretary-Treasurer), 2003-2007, undated (Box 2)
  - Education Department, 1960-1969, undated (Box 3)
  - Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 3)
  - Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 3)
  - Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1949-1959 (Box 3)
  - Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1960-1965 (Box 3)
  - Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Education Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1989-1996 (Box 3)
  - Executive Board, 1975, undated (Box 3)
  - Fliers, 1948-circa 1980s, undated (Box 3)
  - Fliers (Oversize) (I), 1947-1972, undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS004, Folder 4)
  - Fliers (Oversize) (II), 1959-1970 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS001, Folder 2)
  - Fryman, Patsy (Local 4032), 1979, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Gleason, Elaine (Local 1150), 2003 (Box 3)
  - Goldman, Debbie: Curbing Big Brother in the Workplace: the Campaign of CWA Women Against Monitoring of Telephone Operators, 1967-1980, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Grievances and Arbitration, 1968, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Hackney, Ray: Scholarship Fund, undated (Box 3)
  - Hector, Adele (Local 1150 Archivist), 1982, 1996 (Box 3)
  - History: Articles and Scholarly Publications, 1946-1989, undated (Box 3)
  - History: Articles and Scholarly Publications, 1991-1997 (Box 3)
  - History: Newspaper Clippings, 1952-1969 (Box 3)
  - History: Newspaper Clippings, 1970-1989 (Box 3)
  - History: Newspaper Clippings ("In the News"), 1988 (Box 3)
  - History: Newspaper Clippings, 1990-1994 (Box 3)
  - History: Newspaper Clippings, 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  - History: Newspaper Clippings, 2000-2006 (Box 3)
  - History of, 1955- (Box 3)
  - History of, 1955- (Box 3)
  - History of Unionism in the Telephone Industry and the Installation Bargaining Unit, undated (Box 3)
  - Hurlburt, David G. and Barnett, Robert: Poems and Songs from Communication Workers, undated (Box 3)
  - Katz, Carla (Local 1034), 2005-2007 (Box 3)
  - Klauer, James "Jay" (District 7), undated (Box 3)
  - Kramer, Brent (Local 1101), 1974-1985, undated (Box 3)
  - Legislative Activity, 1964, undated (Box 3)
  - Legislative Activity, 1980-1984 (Box 3)
  - Lotz, John (Local 1150), 1981, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Mancino, Larry (Local 1177 and District 1), 2008 (Box 3)
  - Mays, Eugene J. (District 1), 1980 (Box 3)
  - McCabe, James P. (Local 1101), 1966-1987 (Box 3)
  - Meckle, Pat (Local 1150), 1972-1992 (Box 3)
  - Morgan, John T. (Staff), 1997 (Box 3)
  - Myerscough, George (National Director-Long Lines), 1967-1977 (Box 3)
  - National Training Fund for the Communications Industry, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters (The Beacon, the Telephone Flash), 1948-1949 (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS004, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Guild, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Guild-Communications Workers of America Freedom Award Fund Banquet, 2008 (Box 4)
  - Occupational Safety and Health, 1986, undated (Box 4)
  - Organizing Department, 1961-1962, undated (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1959-1975 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1982- (Box 4)
  - Parliamentary Procedure, 1961, undated (Box 4)
  - Pensions, 1982, undated (Box 4)
  - Pierce, Jan (District 1), 1966-1996 (Box 4)
  - Pratt, Jim (Local 1150), 1972-1987 (Box 4)
  - Printing, Publishing and Media Workers Sector, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Quality of Work Life, 1981-1985, undated (Box 4)
  - Radio and Television Programs, 1960, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Rank and File, 1974, undated (Box 4)
  - Rank and File: Final Warning, 1973-1976, undated (Box 4)
  - Reports, 1978, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Reports, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Retired Members Club/Council, 1971-1975, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Roster (Affiliates, Districts, Locals), 2004 (Box 4)
  - Sanchez, Don M. (Local 1150), 1991 (Box 4)
  - Savings and Retirement Trust, 1982, undated (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1951 (Box 4)
  - Serrette, Dennis (Local 1101, New York, NY), 1975-1984 (Box 4)
  - Serrette, Dennis: A Short History of Blacks and Minorities in CWA, 1947-2003, circa 2004 (Box 4)
  - State Workers Organizing Committee (St. Louis, MO), undated (Box 4)
  - Stewards Manuals, undated (Box 4)
  - Strikes, 1947- (Box 4)
  - Strikes: 1947: Nationwide Strike against AT&T, 1987, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Strikes: 1971 (New York), 1971-1996 (Box 4)
  - Strikes: 1983, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Strikes: 1989 (NYNEX), 1989-1999, undated (Box 4)
  - Strikes: 2000 (Verizon) (Box 4)
  - Structure, undated (Box 4)
  - Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Archives Acquires CWA Collection: Articles on, 1995-1998 (Box 4)
  - Task Force 1971: Instructor's Guide (Box 4)
  - Teamsters Raid, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Telephone Company Publications: Employee Handbooks, Pension Plans, 1955, 1974-1980 (Box 4)
  - Training Department: Pamphlets and Publications (I), undated (Box 5)
  - Training Department: Pamphlets and Publications (II), undated (Box 5)
  - Training Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1965-1974 (Box 5)
  - Training Department: Pamphlets and Publications, 1975-1984 (Box 5)
  - United States Department of Labor: Western Union Telegraph Co., 1943-67: Wage Chronology/History, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Van Savage, Helen (Local 1150), 1982-1992, undated (Box 5)
  - Western Union Bargaining Unit, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Western Union: Employee Handbook, undated (Box 5)
  - Venus, Green: Women and Race in the Bell System, 1995, undated (Box 5)
  - Vogel, John N.: The Communication Workers of America: An Outline History, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Walden, Anne (Local 1150), 1983-1995, undated (Box 5)
  - Watkins, Ted (Executive Assistant to National President), 2002 (Box 5)
  - Watts, Glenn (National President), 1983-2002 (Box 5)
  - Women in the Telephone Industry: Articles and Publications, 1958-2003, undated (Box 5)
- Series II: Districts and Locals, 1941-2006; 2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
  - District 1, 1977-2000, undated (Box 5)
  - Division 10 (Long Lines), 1949, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Division 23 (Wisconsin), 1948 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189, 1995-1999 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Directory of Labor Education, 1982-1988 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Directory of Labor Education, 1995-1997 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Mailings, 1994-1996 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Mailings (I), 1997 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Mailings (II), 1997 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Mailings (I), 1998 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Mailings (II), 1998 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Mailings, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Workers' Education Local 189: Newsletters, 1994-1997 (Box 5)
  - Local 201 (IUE/CWA) (Lynn, MA), 2004 (Box 6)
  - Local 1023, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Local 1032 (Ewing, NJ), 1993 (Box 6)
  - Local 1037 (Newark, NJ), 2003-2004 (Box 6)
  - Local 1040 (Trenton, NJ), 2003, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1080 (NJ), 2001 (Box 6)
  - Local 1081 (Essex County, NJ), 2000-2004, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY), 1966-1997, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY): The Bell Wringer, 1973-1981, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY): Membership Contract Committee, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY): Rank and File (Various Groups), 1971-1985, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY): Telephone Workers Legal Defense Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY): United Action Caucus, 1971-1975, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY): United Action (Serial Publication, Issues 1-21), 1971-1973 (Box 6)
  - Local 1101 (New York, NY): Women's Committee on Equity, 1997-1999 (Box 6)
  - Local 1104 (Farmingdale, NY), 1970-2000, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1105 (Bronx, NY), 1993, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1109 (Brooklyn, NY/Union, NJ), 1974-1997 (Box 6)
  - Local 1110, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Local 1116, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Local 1120 (Poughkeepsie, NY), 1993 (Box 6)
  - Local 1121, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1133/1168 (Nurses) (Buffalo, NY), 1985-2004 (Box 6)
  - Local 1150 (New York, NY), undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1150 (New York, NY), 1941-1979 (Box 6)
  - Local 1150 (New York, NY), 1976-2003 (Box 6, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 12)
  - Local 1180 (New York, NY), 1968, 1978, undated (Box 6)
  - Local 1180 (New York, NY), 1984-1996 (Box 6)
  - Local 1182 (Forest Hills, NY), 1999, 2006 (Box 6)
  - Local 1183 (New York, NY), 1960-1979 (Box 6)
  - Local 1365 (North Andover, MA), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Local 2001 (West Virginia Area), 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Local 3062 (Greensboro, NC), 1962 (Box 6)
  - Local 3250 (Atlanta/Decatur, GA), 1984-1986 (Box 6)
  - Local 4309 (Cleveland, OH), undated (Box 6)
  - Local 4351 (Cincinnati, OH), 1959 (Box 6)
  - Local 9400 (Paramount, CA), 1992 (Box 6)
  - Local 9407 (Merced, CA), 1953, 2005 (Box 6)
  - Local 9410 (San Francisco, CA): Militant Action Caucus, 1978 (Box 6)
- Series III: Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008; 5 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons
  - Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008 (Box 7)
  - Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008 (Box 8)
  - Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008 (Box 9)
  - Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008 (Box 10)
  - Agreements and Contracts, 1947-2008 (Box 11)